You
The following was recorded live at the 2026 Parish Life Conference of the Antiochian Orthodox
Diasis of Miami and the Southeast, held June 10-13 in Springdale, Arkansas.
We begin with a short presentation, followed by a live Q&A with a...
other audience.
We'll see if you clap afterwards.
That's the real test.
That's the question.
Yeah.
You know, there's one of my favorite memes that has popped up.
You guys know what memes are, right?
Okay.
I'm just checking.
Generation check.
You know, one of my favorite memes that has popped up in recent days, recent years on
The
The ortho web is a Twitter exchange
in which on Twitter someone wrote,
there is no blank outside the Orthodox Church.
And the response to that was parking.
There is no parking outside the Orthodox Church.
And so the first question I have for all of you
is how many of you is that true for your parish
where there's parking problems.
at your church.
Yes, welcome to the Orthodox Convert search.
And that's what I want to talk about as my presentation.
What we're going to do is these sessions
are going to be mostly Q&A.
And so you can see there's two microphones up here
up front, which you can use to come and stand
and ask questions.
But the way that we're going to begin
is with each of us giving a short presentation.
because it's kind of weird to just say,
okay, ask questions.
Yeah, that's a little weird.
So I wanna talk today.
I have no idea what Father Stevens doing tomorrow.
I'm gonna talk about mouse habitats tomorrow.
And the great thing is, is 50-50,
whether that's actually true or not.
I mean, it's true.
So we're gonna give a short presentation
and then have a conversation.
So if you have a question that occurs to you
while the
is happening in a righted down so you don't forget.
If you have an angry comment that you would like to give
during the presentation, write it down so that you don't forget.
And if you just do, ooh, ooh, ooh, ooh,
like in Welcome Back Codder,
it's another generation of check there.
Then we probably will not call on you
because we have provided microphones that you can stand in front of
to ask your questions.
So before I begin actually just to kind of check the audience,
audience. How many of you?
How many of you have listened to the Lord of Spirits podcast?
Okay.
All right.
We're in a mostly safe room.
It seems it's good.
Or disgruntled.
Or that could be also the case.
I listen to still five minutes of one episode and those guys.
Yeah, so I want to talk about the Convert Search.
And I travel a decent amount and wherever I go I ask people
about how their parishes are experiencing it.
And so it raises a lot of interesting questions
And I think...
that many of our clergy and certainly a lot of our laity have been caught a little off guard by this.
You know, I mean how many of you launched a big evangelistic program and that's why your parking is terrible now.
Right, no one did this.
It was not a thing we all got together and said let's do that apostolic thing we've been supposed to be doing all these years.
No, no, it's pretty clear that God has sent these people.
And the place I want to begin is to actually ask the question, what does it...
it mean to convert because I think that often it's sort of taken for granted that conversion
means becoming a member.
You know, I didn't use to be a member of the Orthodox Church and now I'm a member.
I did the things I had to do to become a member.
So now I'm Orthodox.
And but it's actually very hazy for a lot of people.
I've seen people on, you know, X formerly known as Twitter.
Does anyone actually call it X?
No, we all still say they're tweeting, right?
And then in news articles it says X.
And then in parentheses, formerly known as Twitter, because no one calls it X except for
the guy who owns the Tesla company, I guess.
I've actually seen people saying, I'm Orthodox, and then when someone says, oh, which Paris
do you go to, they say, I haven't visited one yet.
Which is kind of hilarious if you're the kind of person who goes to a Paris life conference.
Because you know, you all have been to church at least a couple of times, I hope.
But there are-
are many people for whom this is somewhere down the line
that becoming an Orthodox Christian
is primarily about making a kind of ideological decision.
And indeed, this arises from the Protestant culture,
especially the evangelical Protestant culture
of the United States, where you can say,
today I became a Christian.
And what you mean by that is I decided,
I decided deep within my heart to do something.
Right? And I think...
a lot of people that's their notion of becoming Orthodox too is they made a decision.
And indeed, I mean, how many of you were raised in evangelical context?
Like I was, yes.
So y'all probably very familiar with the language of, I made a decision for Christ.
And that's the thing that checks off the big box that says, oh, you're a Christian now,
which of course that's a very foreign way of thinking, way of being for an Orthodox Christian.
You know, you made a decision, oh great.
Okay, now there's some things to do.
So what does it actually mean to convert?
I think one of the keys to this problem is found at the beginning of the baptism service,
where there is what in the fancy Greek terms is what's called the apotoxys and the cindoxys.
And at the first one, the apotoxys is asking the person to deny the devil, right, that I reject the devil.
And indeed in many forms of this, there's the whole spitting thing, which is the
one part that a lot of people remember.
But it's, do you renounce the devil
and all his works and all his service and all his pride,
or pomp as it's sometimes translated, this pomp,
he renounces pomp, I love that.
Do you renounce him, right?
And that's the upotaxis, which means literally means,
I'm no longer ordered with him and his bunch, right?
And then the Cindacces,
in our older books it says,
Does that unite thyself to Christ?
But now...
actually a better translation is our newer book that says,
does thou align thyself with Christ?
You could also say, although it would sound a little weird,
do you pledge your allegiance to Christ?
And that's the Cindex, he's to be ordered with Christ
and his saints.
Actually, I still need power here,
because I can watch my laptop is dying slowly,
slowly, not immediately.
And so at that moment you're saying,
I'm leaving this bunch.
joining this bunch and that's a very 3D experience, right?
And you're doing it at the door of the nave, the idea being
that you're about to cross over that threshold and come in.
And so there is this turning away from the devil
and turning to Christ.
A lot of people will define conversion
as also turning away from sin and turning towards Christ.
And that's, especially for those of you raised even
to a local, like you're very familiar with that kind of language.
And that turns out to be correct.
You can keep that one.
You're turning away from senior
from the devil, from his bunch, and you're joining yourself to Christ.
It's not just a decision, it's an actual movement from one to another.
And so that's what it means in the most basic sense to convert.
Converting Americans is a kind of a curious thing.
Because in the United States, we're so used to conversion being a choice.
Right? Like I decided to become Orthodox.
I decided to become a Baptist.
I decided to become a Pentecostal.
I met suddenly deeply weird and I decided to become a Scientologist because I was also
a very big bank account.
For those of you who that was funny, I'm very honored that you know what that means.
For Americans, it's a self-conscious choice.
I was this and now I've decided to become this.
And this presents, I think, a kind of problem for the traditional Orthodox consciousness.
And by that I don't mean treat-
as in a holy tradition, I mean the convention that we've experienced for centuries upon
centuries, which is that in most of what we'll call Orthodox countries, which use that
term advisedly, by the way, if you actually know something about all those countries,
in most Orthodox countries, no one decides to be Orthodox. Your parents bring you to church
when you're a baby and you be your Orthodox. I'm sure that describes probably many people
in this room. How many of you here were your parents decided to make you an Orthodox
Christian. Yes.
This is a very convert heavy room.
But there are some of you, you know,
your parents decided to bring you,
and your Orthodox because they brought you,
and then they raised you that way.
And so there's this kind of question
of inherited religion versus a self-conscious religion.
What's interesting about America is that we know
from the significant loss of people raised Orthodox
were no longer in the church,
that self-conscious religion has come for us all.
You know, for those of you whose parents brought you
to the
the Orthodox Church as a little baby the first time.
The reason that you are still here
is because you have decided to stay.
You had to make a choice to stay.
Your neighborhood is probably not an Orthodox neighborhood.
Your town is not an Orthodox town.
It's not just the thing that everybody does.
You had to decide.
It's a self-conscious choice.
And this has good and bad elements to it.
But I think in a lot of ways it connects us much more
to the many, many centuries of...
sort of inherited Orthodox identity, but rather to the first few centuries of Christianity
in which to make the choice to be a Christian meant you could die.
It meant that you were stepping outside of the worship of the gods of your family, or
that you were stepping outside of the tradition of the scribes and the Pharisees if you were
a Judean becoming a Christian.
It was a choice.
saying that our time exactly mirrors that time.
But in so-
many ways it does. And I think that's really an important thing for us to realize that
a lot of the way that Orthodox Christians talk is about trying to reconstruct some kind
of Christendom. Like, when we lost it, you know, the Turks took Constantinople or the Muslims
invaded the Middle East or whatever point you want to point at, you know, or all those
glorious monarchies became republic nation states in the 1920s century and so we lost it.
We need to get back to that.
I mean.
I mean, I don't know if there's any avowed monarchists in the room or people who want
a grand orthodox empire, but that is not going to happen in your lifetime.
Just accept that now.
You can pine for that.
Maybe that's the ideal, I don't know, but it's not going to happen.
Where we are is where we are.
So that kind of brings us a little bit to the question of how it is that people show
up at our doors.
How many here would you say that when...
people show up the doors and you ask them how did you hear about this that the first
thing they say has something to do with the internet.
Yeah, almost everybody, almost everybody.
Gone are the days where, like when I became an Orthodox Christian almost 30 years ago now,
most people said, oh, I was reading Church history and you know, I looked up, you know,
in a phone book or I used altavista, who remembers altavista?
Yes, ask.
Gee, it was clear.
That's the thing.
I remember when Yahoo was trying to compile a catalog of every website on the internet.
You remember that?
That was really a thing back in 1996.
Back when Fear Sputers Day off was only a 10-year-old movie.
Because today, June 11th, 2026, it is a 40-year-old movie.
Yes, there's another generation check for you
took his day off back in 1986.
Yeah, most people are showing up because of the internet
in one way or another.
And there's a lot of ways that they're encountering
orthodoxy on the internet that are healthy and wholesome.
And then there's a lot of ways that are other.
And that presents a lot of pastoral challenges
for our clergy and for the laity that are trying
to help them come in.
And actually I vote.
I think five times in the last 24 hours with other clergy here,
I've had a couple of clergy like, well, what do you do when someone says they've been listening to?
And I'm not going to name any names, but fill in a name here.
And then that's the reason that they're here.
Like, what do you do about that?
And I mean, my advice is to say, thank God you're here.
But now it's time to do this thing in 3D.
Because the Orthodox life is lived in 3D.
It's okay if your introduction Orthodox Christianity was centered on some
or some argument or whatever it might be.
It's okay.
It's okay if you feel like the world is insane
and you're looking for some kind of safe haven in the storm.
And maybe your idea of a safe haven
is not exactly what the Orthodox Church is.
Maybe if it's some political reason you showed up.
And it's okay, however you got here, God brought you here,
but now you're here, right?
So if the reason you came is not really completely about Christ,
it's time to make it about Christ.
And if you're pleased.
sees that you're not quite there yet, it's incumbent upon him to say, okay, well, let's take some time, you know, to center you on Christ, right?
And so then the question is like, well, what does Catechesis actually look like? For many decades, Catechesis and the Orthodox Church has largely been what I call the Orthodoxy 101 approach, which could be essentially accomplished by handing them Mitch Paulton College to his
This was Wuer's book, The Orthodox Church, and saying, read this.
Like those are the topics, right?
I mean, we've all experienced that probably in some level.
And so at the end, what you get is from that class is someone who can pass a 101 college
course in orthodoxy, which is not a bad thing to be able to do.
But as I've sometimes had conversations with clergy, I'll say, you know, father, imagine
in your mind the ideal parishioner.
right? That's doing all the things that you tell your people to do. Is your
cataclysis training people for that? And in most cases, the answer that I've
gotten from Clarsie when I asked that question is, hmm, because they realize they've
been doing the orthodoxy 101 thing, which I mean I know it's some pairs as the
classes literally called orthodoxy 101. So don't, don't, don't, don't at me bro
So, you know, but I mean, I guess...
I think there's nothing wrong with that.
Like there's nothing wrong with learning that information.
But this sort of assumption that training orthodox Christians means like sort of taking
like fired up Bible-believe in Baptists and adding icons and stuff like that.
Like that's, that should not be a thing.
And it's increasingly not a thing.
Because the world's supply of fervent Bible-believing Baptists is actually waning.
more and more people being raised without religion at all,
or the religion they're being raised with
is not that old-time religion.
It's something else.
And so that means that what should, in my opinion,
what should Catechese be?
Well, think of that faithful parishioner
and then train them to do that.
Train them to be people who come to worship very regularly.
And I'll say, since I'm back in the South,
not to throw shade on my previous place.
that I lived, but just the culture of orthodoxy in the South
is different than it is in the Northeast
where I came from.
I remember the first time I was back at all Saints in Raleigh.
And orthros was about to begin.
I look out and there's a hundred people standing there
waiting for it to begin.
I was like, is this the Twilight Zone?
Because in most of the rest of the country,
no one goes to that service.
There might be two or three.
And so the habits of some parishes
are different than the habits of others.
And
It's very difficult to train when a parish has bad habits, it's difficult to train even
the new people with good habits.
They're like, well, why should I do something differently than everybody else here, Father?
Which is a hard question to answer.
But those are the things I think that Catechese needs to focus on especially is here's how
you be a faithful corporate worshipper.
Here's how you be someone who faithfully praise at home.
Here's how you be someone who gives alms faithfully.
Here's how you be someone who volunteers faithfully in your parish.
Here's how.
That's really the big question is the word how.
And I mentioned, of course, there can be difficult to get people to take on the habits
of everyone else.
This was especially true in the early church because if you look at the earliest sort of
catechisms, they're actually not largely what you would call about theology.
They're mostly about behavior.
Here's how you stop being a demon worth...
to being pagan.
Here's how you live in such a way
with all the morality of a Christian.
Because for a lot of them, unless they were raised as part
of the Judean people, that stuff was not taken for granted.
Like, when St. Paul has to tell a guy in Corinth
stop sleeping with your mother-in-law,
I think on some level, he was probably like, well, wait,
what?
That's what you guys do here?
You don't sleep with your mother-in-law,
or wherever else you think you should be sleeping with?
because that was completely normal in their world.
And so incorporating people into a different way of living,
a different set of habits can be very difficult
when most of the people there are new.
And indeed, I asked, so like the frame of reference
that I have now, is in Raleigh, I asked Father David there
at one point about a year ago, I said,
Father, of the 500 plus people showing up on Sunday morning,
how many have been Orthodox for less than five years?
and heat.
told me more than half.
How many of you are seeing something like that at your parish where the majority are
now new?
So this is awesome and cool and beautiful on the one hand, but scary and difficult on
the other because it used to be we would tell the catacumans just look just blend in with
everybody else.
And now it's like, well I'm new my hear myself.
so that creates an instability.
And so that's one of the things that we have to deal with now.
So at this moment here in 2026, and this is where I'm going to wrap up,
so begin to think of your questions.
Now we have simultaneously a convert surge,
right, and make no mistake. We all know that we didn't do anything to make this happen.
God has sent these people to us. A convert surge is happening simultaneously with a clergy shortage.
Right?
And so what does that mean?
In some cases, there's dozens of catacumins.
In some cases, there's hundreds of catacumins,
massive groups of people.
How many of your churches have more than you've ever seen before?
Yeah.
And when there's both a convert surge
and a clergy shortage going on at the same time,
and here's another tough thing,
I said something tough to the monarchists in the room.
There's a tough thing for everybody else in the room right now.
It means...
the rationing of pastoral care.
Every time I utter that sentence,
it's a little scary to me now.
Like the idea that there's rationing of pastoral care,
that you're not gonna be able to talk to your priest
as often as you want.
You're gonna probably have to make an appointment.
It's gonna probably have a time limit
because there's not enough of him and there's way more of you.
So I mean number one obviously you know if you're if you're mature
in the face, consider ordination, guys.
Ask how you can help.
But also, I've had some people say, well, shouldn't the convert
search bring us more clergy?
I really hope that it does, but not today.
That would be supremely irresponsible.
I went to seminary with multiple guys who
were sent after being orthodox for like a year,
or in one case, a month.
They were sent to seminary, and the majority of them now
are deposed ex priests.
and their marriages are a wreck.
You know, don't do that.
It doesn't just ruin a family.
It really is harmful for the flock.
Once in a while it works out okay.
I mean there are cases where a guy that's ordained
relatively quickly it works out okay,
but it is an absolute gamble.
So we're gonna have to wait on the converse
search to generate more clergy.
We're talking probably five, eight, 10 years, right?
Because don't you want them to be Orthodox
for several years before they even go to seminary at all
or whatever.
clergy training, we're giving them.
And then that training should be years long as well, right?
So it's not going to happen immediately.
There's, in the meantime, there's going to be rashing
a pastoral care.
In the meantime, it's going to be a whole lot of,
you get 10 minutes for confession or whatever it is.
I feel, I don't know if Father David is from Raleigh is in the room,
but if he is, I'm very sorry about mentioning your name
over and over again, but it's your party, my frame of reference
father.
But I was asking him, I was like, Father,
how many confessions do you hear?
And he's like
Well, I think it's about 40 or 50 a week.
And so I said, Father, in one year of your priesthood,
you're hearing more confessions
than I have heard in almost 20 years of priesthood,
just to give you some sense of the scale, right?
So there's absolutely the rationing of pastoral care
that's just as a reality right now.
So a slightly shorter route to some level of help
is Deacons and Ciadna Saba has called for what he says,
is an army of
an army of deacons, he said there's really five or six
per parish, which amen, amen.
This is by the way the apostolic model,
way more deacons than priests and bishops.
Way more deacons.
I think our archdiocese right now has the best,
we have the best ratio of deacons per parish
of any orthodox jurisdiction in the US,
and that is largely thanks to the vision of Metropolitan
Philip of Blessed Memory, who just pushed really hard
for this starting in the 1970s and early 80s.
I think our ratio is something like 0.8 or 0.9 per perish.
So it's almost one per perish.
So we got a little ways to go to get five or six per perish.
But clearly we need that.
But the biggest thing that we can do right now,
and that does not require years of training,
is for mature laymen to step up.
To step up to teach, to step up to mentor,
to step up to help take care of their clergy families,
takes some pressure off of them.
Right? To step up to help integrate these people into parish life into your life.
They just started doing something in Raleigh, which is every new catacum and gets a couple
in the parish, assigned to them to be their sort of, this is not the official term, but
this is how I'm describing it, their catacuses buddies. You know, that these are the first
people they should go to to connect, to integrate, to say what am I supposed to do?
to begin to form relationships with them and who knows, maybe...
sometimes that'll become their God parents.
Doesn't have to be, but it'll help to integrate.
Another thing that is really super important here
is that parishes really need to focus
on the ministry of practical love.
Many parishes, people, they commute there,
they go to church there and then they go home.
And if it's healthy, then they'll linger
and hang out with each other for a while afterwards,
which is such a beautiful thing.
The lingering, I love that.
But if there's someone with a real need in the parish,
often it goes unknown, or maybe the priest only knows about it.
It's time for us to really love each other
in not just a, hey, I love you man, kind of way.
It's really time for us to do that.
And not only does that help to,
not only is that what we're supposed to be doing,
because Christ told us to do that,
but also it meets the needs of the people
that we already have in the parish,
and helps to make it so that the parish
is not largely fixed on one kind of social,
is socially...
economic range which can be the case.
In fact, in America by the way,
the highest levels of church going are associated
with higher levels of income,
meaning that poor people are having a hard time
being integrated into church.
That's on us.
It's absolutely on us.
And if we actually met their needs,
met their material needs,
that might look different.
But the other thing is,
is a lot of the people that are coming to our doors
these days, they are used to the world beating them up
and not caring about the...
at all. And if they come in and their needs are being met, maybe the first thing they
experience is a free meal. I actually talked to a pastor in Glasgow in Scotland. And he
has this amazing ministry with students at the University of Glasgow. And he told me that
he invited one of these students to a meal. And then at the end, the student asked, and
how much does that cost? And he said, nothing. And the student was like, what? You know,
the old.
saying there's no such thing as a free lunch,
except in the church.
It should be in the church.
So like if you have to pay for coffee hour,
please stop that.
That's such a terrible thing.
Cause you're sifting out people who,
they didn't come, they can't do that.
They can't do that when you make them pay for coffee hour
or whatever it might be.
So yeah, that emphasis on practical love.
So with the kind of pressure that we're experiencing
just the press of people and then also right now the shortage of clergy.
I mean, we're working on this.
This problem is being worked on on multiple levels, but we can't just say,
well, that's up to the bishops.
You get guys better solve it, you know?
No matter how hard the bishops work, and if even if they put in place
perfect plans today, which we're still figuring out what the perfect plans are,
by the way, if they put all those in place today,
it's going to be years before the shortage will actually be overcome years.
So right now...
What the rest of us can do is to step up
and to really minister to each other
and not see ourselves as religious consumers.
Now, I know that those of you
the kind of people come to parish life conference
you are the people who are stepping up.
I know that.
You wouldn't come to a parish life conference
if you didn't care about that kind of thing.
It's not the ideal vacation.
Right?
You spent a lot of money to be here
and you came here because you care about your parish
and you want your parish to do well.
You want to minister to your parish.
So spread this spirit to other people.
You know, every parish has what they call the 80-20 rule,
which is, you know, 20% of the people do 80% of the work.
You need to work on, we all need to work on that ratio a little bit.
And here's the kicker. Here's the last thing I'm gonna say about all that.
A stronger emphasis on the ministry of lay people,
and there's a lot of things that I didn't mention, like, you know,
visiting the sick, for instance.
That doesn't, you do not have to have a
CASSIC to visit a person.
in a hospital or to visit someone at home who can't come to church.
You do not.
All these kinds of things, the increase of lay ministry is how we should have been doing
church all along.
Clericalism that we're all experiencing, where it's the idea of like, well, Father,
you know, he's the full-time employee.
That was always a distortion.
And now we have a big opportunity.
to push back against that distortion.
And here's the thing, if we don't do that,
then what will happen is the intensity of people
who are barely categorized in huge numbers in our parishes,
because we are not getting a handle on them,
will create your peaceful parish might well go to something
being other than peaceful, because people will not be formed in Christ.
They'll just become members.
Parishes might split.
A lot of people who have been going to your church for a long time and are like, wow,
there's suddenly six times as many people here as there were just five years ago, may
feel like they're no longer welcome and don't want to be there anymore.
And so the time has come for us to engage in this kind of lay ministry on a level that
I'm not saying no one's been doing anything, you know, that's obviously not the case.
But we have a big opportunity and if we don't take the opportunity, then I fear that there's
going to be some level of collapse that's going to go on in a lot of communities.
You know, we're rejoicing in the numbers and that's awesome.
It's amazing.
It's, wow, I mean, no one sitting here has seen this kind of thing in their lifetime.
never happen in the history of orthodoxy in a-
America, ever.
I've studied it very closely, right?
But if we don't meet it well, it could actually destroy
the church in America, right?
We could have schisms, we could have parish collapses,
we could have all kinds of stuff like this.
You know, at clergy quitting because they just can't take
it anymore, which is absolutely a thing, absolutely a thing.
So that's what I have to say is kind of an introductory-
You know, sort of comments.
I'm sorry, I don't have anything to say about,
what was it, mouse habitats?
Mouse habitats.
Get that tomorrow.
The reason we had Father Andrew go first today is,
since I was a kid when I get my dinner plate,
I'd always eat the vegetables first
to get that over with.
And then whenever it was best, I'd save that for last
to sort of keep it.
That's right.
Keep that taste in my mouth, as I say.
Exactly.
So yeah, so I'm the vegetables.
I'm the broccoli as it were.
Although I do kind of like rockin'
He's good for you.
Right.
Just not as pleasant.
I mean, fried okra is very good.
Yeah?
Yes, back on the land of fried okra.
So happy to be here.
The land of sweet tea.
Below the sweet tea line.
So, but yeah, I want to hear it.
So please, come, I want to hear about how your parishes
are experienced, the convert surge.
Ideas that you have, if your parishes
implement something new.
respond to the just press of people that you're experiencing. Here's two
microphones lineup. Let's hear from you.
How did the sun cross once carried by the pagans of the Baltic North become the
cross of Jesus? How did the last pagan nation of medieval Europe first encounter
Christ in the Orthodox Church.
Forodotus said these people were known the swervans.
Khan with us, Salah Pilgrim is through the sometimes strange, sometimes surprising street
of the Dwellenia.
The green-norded land poised between east and west.
Thank you, Father's for being here.
I know you're both well aware of all these, the sin flux of converts, inquires, catechumans.
It seems the vast majority tend to be men.
I'm just wondering is there something?
we can do better to attract more women?
Is it even a problem in your mind?
Do you think that there's something that we're not doing
right or do you think women may just be coming later on?
OK, this is a great question.
And part of why it's a good question
is not just because in itself it's a good question.
But it's actually a question, and I hope I can help a little bit
of ignorance that exists right now.
So there are people actually statistically
studying the convert search.
This is actually a thing.
And unfortunately, the people who write articles in mainstream newspapers are not talking to
those people as much as they should when they write their articles.
Because the impression that they've given is, and I'm sure you've all heard this, that
the Convert Surge is largely a bunch of extreme right-wing young men.
How many of you heard that before?
Yes, Reddit and newspaper articles, whatever.
How many of you does that describe your parish?
I saw one hand.
Yeah.
Right.
So, those who are tracking the convert surge,
which basically begins in the wake of the pandemic,
that's essentially the beginning point.
The point where we start seeing spikes is about 2021,
when we start coming back to church, you know,
in significant numbers.
In the initial bump,
Bump, because the convert surge actually has had two...
peaks, which is a lot of people don't know this. The initial peak, there was a plurality
of young men, it's true. There was a plurality of young men, meaning not the majority, not
more than half, but the largest group. The second peak, now, the dominant group is young
families. How many of you are seeing that at your parishes? Yes, so welcome to the reality.
This is the truth.
Which is part of the reason that I say to people, even if the search stops tomorrow, which probably not.
Even if the search stops tomorrow, a demographic change has occurred within the Orthodox Church that's going to reverberate now for decades.
Because all these young families are going to be having kids, and it turns out by the way, here's not a good statistic for you.
The fertility rate of Orthodox Christians in America, do you know what it is?
Four.
Replacement rate is 2.1.
The country in general is below replacement rate.
people have more kids.
Yes.
Yes, yes.
It could be a bright future as long as we're not dumb.
So like I said, even if it stops tomorrow, the demographic changes occurred in Orthodox
in America.
Like for instance, I'll give you an example, the OCA diocese of Eastern Pennsylvania,
which no one is looking at in terms of studying the converse surge, except certain friends
a vine because there's parishes closing there.
It's just largely not-
especially Northeastern Pennsylvania,
multiple parishes, one priest.
Not per parish, one priest with multiple parishes, right?
What's going on there is their total population
has been going down for years and years and years, right?
They've been losing people.
But if you look more closely at the actual demographics
of that diocese in the last five years,
while the number has still gone down,
the population has been getting younger,
which means that probably within a few years
You
It's going to flip and it's going to actually begin to grow.
Not as fast as y'all are seen in the South.
Definitely not as fast, but it's still affecting that area as well.
But to answer the question of what about young women?
There is a whole world of articles out there being written about how orthodoxy is unattractive
for harmful to women, to young women, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
which would be an interesting thesis if we had,
within the last, say, five years,
you know, when this all begins,
had adopted some new thing
where we're like, suddenly, we're not attractive to women
where we were before.
Because before the surge, by the way,
there are more women than men in church.
I think that might still be the case, actually, a little bit.
We suddenly adopted some new thing,
but as we have firmly established,
we did not do anything new.
There is not some new program.
Certainly all the jurisdictions in America do not get together and say, let's do anything
together.
It's not happening.
Right?
No, what has happened is, and this is what's really important to understand, orthodoxy
in America right now in many ways is unique, but in many ways is not unique.
And the most significant way in which we're not unique is that...
The demographic that's lagging behind in terms of religious participation is young women.
This is across the board, every religious group in America.
It's not just the Orthodox.
Right?
There's something about female zoomers and the experience that they've had in life
that is disconnecting them from religious experience, whether it's church or some other
kind of religion.
So we're looking at a societal thing.
We're looking at a society level thing.
and we're not exempt from it.
You know?
But I think that I've heard people say,
you know, the young men are coming now,
the young women will follow.
I hope that's true.
But I also know that the marriage rate
is going down in America.
So not necessarily, right?
Just the marriage rate is going down.
Because young people are spending less time with each other,
they have more and more relationships
with people they've never met in 3D.
Right?
to turn into marriage.
So I hope that they will follow.
But I think that the key thing that we need, I think the best thing that we need is for
mature women to mentor younger women.
Men need men, women need women.
Men cannot provide to women what women can provide, and vice versa.
So we'll see, as societal, the shearing forces are destructive to young women as much as
they are, we'll see what happens.
But yeah, there's nothing special about orthodoxy that's making it.
unattractive to young women.
There's a lot of people saying that,
but there's literally no good evidence for that.
And again, it's not continued to be just
a bunch of young guys coming in.
I know that some parents that is definitely the case,
but it's largely families now.
And so I think it's incumbent upon families,
especially to find the people in their life.
The single Zoomer or Millennial,
Or maybe some left.
over generation exers like ourselves who just never connected and never whatever and just to take
them in and make them part of the family in some way because the loneliness is literally killing
many of us. So yeah, it's a great question that was asked. I don't know, do you have anything to
see about that, Father? I do. Okay. Yeah, because I think the place where the rubber meets the road
with this is that when you have young men and not young men.
young women, it's the marriage thing.
Right, because, especially because we're telling young men,
where should you go to find a spouse?
To the church.
And then they go there and like,
the youngest unmarried woman is 63.
Right?
Um.
And they're like, I don't know.
I remember, a year ago, we moved my 18 year old daughter
at that time to North Carolina
before my family came back.
and I told her I said
in the Vongalia, you're gonna have a line.
You don't have to accept the first person in line.
You can take applications, we'll review them together.
And a month later she found the guy.
She's just getting me in October.
Sorry, she's off the market, guys.
Yes, you may not have my daughter.
Sorry, anyway, sir.
Yeah.
No, so, yeah, don't think that just because father Josiah
when on Girl's Gone Bible that that's...
solve the whole problem.
I'm glad he did that.
I am glad he did that.
And he may be the only priest who could have done that,
kind of gotten away with it with his bonafid.
Leon Nixon could go to China?
Yes, exactly.
Old click on proverb.
So yeah, so it's the marriage issue, right?
And my explanation for why younger women are...
less interested in church and religion in general is precisely related to marriage.
You look at the average age of a woman getting married, and it is much higher than it's
ever been.
And that used to be, so back in the day, you would have kids, they grow up, they'd be in
the teen group at church. They'd go off to college, you wouldn't see them.
And then they get married, and especially once they had a kid,
then the whole family would come back to the church.
That's when they would start thinking that way,
if they drifted off.
But statistically that doesn't happen anymore.
Right, but especially if young women are not even getting married,
then the potential for that happening is pushed out,
sort of way into the future.
I'm not going to say I recommend missionary dating,
where you go out.
deliberately start dating a girl in order to convert her. But I will say this. I will
say this. I've already done one. I've got three more weddings coming up this year. That
means I've got four weddings this year. We're a small parish. I have only done four weddings
total in the last eight years I was there. And all four of these weddings are people in
their early 20s.
And in every case, at the beginning of the relationship, the young woman was not Orthodox.
And they started coming to church with the young man who they were dating and made their
own decision to come into the church, right, as part of that process.
So not missionary dating, no bother with the...
all-tierier motives, right?
But in a healthy relationship between a man and a man,
say, I'm old school, this will offend people,
but ask anyone on Twitter, I'm a misogynist.
So I'll just go ahead and play into it.
I'm sorry, this is how I and my sisters were raised.
Was the idea that when it comes to spiritual matters,
the husband is the leader.
And then in a healthy relationship,
that
the wife is going to follow that lead.
And I see that play out, and it works well when it plays out.
And I think it's just kind of true that if you have a young man
who has really been integrated into the life of the church,
at Orthodoxy, is really important to him,
an important part of his life.
And he has an active spiritual life where he's praying,
where he's coming to church, he's fully involved.
then someone who they get involved.
If they're attracted to him, that's going to be part of why they're attracted to him.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And that's going to make them very open, right, to coming in and becoming part of the church.
Now it helps I'm in a 70% Roman Catholic town.
So there's a lot of lapsed Catholic girls out there who have stopped going to church, right?
And this can now bring them in.
But I think that's part of the answer with younger women.
because addict totally
my parish, I've had women joining single women but they are literally in their like 50s and 60s
and then I have a lot a bunch of guys in their 20s that doesn't dovetail so.
More questions come on line up.
Father Siva and I studied mice in Baton Rouge for 10 years so I'm looking forward to your telecom.
You're probably going to know all about what I'm going to talk about that.
And Father Andrew I guess because the internet has been so instrumental
We have Al Gore to thank for the converse.
search.
Al Gore.
Once again, we might be dating myself with that.
I really appreciated what you had to say about orthodoxy being a three-dimensional experience
and really even four-dimensional right because it spans over the course of time as well.
And that's kind of the case for us.
I mean, we've been orthodox for about 20 years.
We spent 16 years in a Greek parish.
And so my question is more about the anionchian archdiocese specifically.
We didn't see as much of that surge.
in a parish that was traditionally Greek.
What do you think the differences might be there?
Okay, another good question,
which I will try to tread appropriately.
So as I've traveled and asked people,
so basically I have some actual data
and then massive amounts of anecdotal conversations
with people about these things.
And some images have kind of emerged out of that,
which I keep testing them to see if they're true
and they mostly seem to be.
as to how the surge is affecting different parishes.
So if you are in an area where there's only two or three
Orthodox churches in a significant metro area,
all of those parishes are seeing people come.
Right?
All of them.
If you are in a metro area where there are dozens
and dozens and dozens of Orthodox churches,
like let's say Chicago.
So Cook County, Ohio still has the largest number
of Orthodox Christians in any county in the United States.
And if you go to it
If you just randomly pick a North-Edox church in Chicago,
there is a strong chance when you walk in the door
that you will hear a language that you do not understand.
Very strong chance.
And that's because there was, you know,
high concentrations of immigrant communities there,
completely understandable.
Like, I earlier this year, I did a retreat
at a Greek parish in the north part of Chicago,
and it was made very clear to me
that North Chicago Greeks are a different village
then south kutshaka
if anybody is from Chicago Greeks, which is kind of its own country,
you know what I'm talking about, they say, oh, the North Parish is the South Parish.
So, they have almost a sense, they have the same bishop.
They are within like five miles of each other, but they still have a sense of where, you know,
but it's that strength of identity, right?
And I was at this North Chicago Greek Parish and they said,
father, you know, you're talking about all these conversions happening.
And it's true what you're saying. We have five catacuments.
We have never seen this many.
So even there they were being affected.
But one of the things that's really interesting
that's happening is I actually,
I was contacted by a priest in a Rust Belt town.
I won't say which one, but a Rust Belt town
kind of somewhere in the Midwest ish.
And he said to me, you know,
you're talking about this father,
but we just haven't seen it or a parish.
We just haven't seen it.
And what was interesting to me was that I knew,
I was friends with a priest, another priest in that same town
at a different parish which is was filling
up with new people.
So within a couple of miles of each other, you have two parishes, one that's seeing a lot
of people and then another one that's seeing no new people.
So what's the difference?
One is, I mean you could imagine what it might be, but let's pull it down.
One is ready to receive people and one is not for whatever reason.
There's a lot of different reasons that might be.
A big reason is language.
That's probably the biggest one.
But another one might be unfriendliness.
There was a parish that I visited in Northeastern Pennsylvania where occasionally when it snowed
really heavily the seminarians, the seminarians of St. T. Cans would go and suddenly this parish
had a big pile of kids in it that they did normally did not.
And there was a passive aggressive sign on the door to the nave saying, control your children.
You think that's a kid-friendly parish?
I hope they took that sign down.
That's years ago.
I hope they took it down.
But there's all kinds of ways.
And that was the fully English...
speaking parish. There's all kinds of ways to not be ready to receive people.
So in areas where you've got lots and lots of churches to choose from, the surge is going
to go the path of least resistance. It's going to go to the place that's going to be in
the United States, English speaking, friendly people. And actually, these days, that's kind
of almost all you need, right? If you're not receiving people, you really should ask
yourself what is going on with your community at this moment.
decades past, that was not always the case. But now the spigot has turned on full, you know?
But, you know, that's just to get people in the door. Receiving them well and planting them well,
that's another question that some of what I was talking about earlier. But so there are places where
there's many, many churches and some are growing and some are withering at the same time.
Okay? In some places where there's only maybe one or two Orthodox churches and then for 30 or 45
ministers, not another. And let's say one or both of those parishes is focused on an image.
community and maybe always has been what's happening in those cases is the
parish culture is rapidly shifting in very short time. I was talking to a woman
who is a relatively isolated parish in Florida which had been traditionally
associated with a particular immigrant community and she said now we have all
these people at Orthross it used to be no one came to Orthross now we have all
all these people that are...
and the growth growths, dozens of them,
and none of them speak the language
that is being used in that service.
All these people have shown up,
and so what's happening is the character
of the parish is flipping,
because there's nowhere else for them to go,
which is a really interesting thing that's occurring,
and is very destabilizing for a community.
Just imagine that.
Again, people who've been there for decades
suddenly feeling that they're not welcome
in their own church, which we can say,
well, tough, you need to be more welcoming.
No, we need to figure out how to integrate people
together if...
because in that scenario what's going to happen is either the converts will kind of overwhelm
the parish. That's maybe the sort of the best case scenario in that case or what will happen
is they will not integrate and there'll be some kind of split. Like we're going to go off
here and start our own thing because there's always another bishop to shop for in North
of doxia in America which is terrible. This is terrible. So what's really been happening,
conclusion is all of the processes and
And movements that we've been seeing in orthodoxy in America
that I've been going on at a particular speed
for decades upon decades now, they have all accelerated
because of the sheer number of people that are coming,
which is on the one hand, we're very happy to see all of them,
but it's also a little, it can be very destabilizing
for a parish.
So yeah, it really depends, but I predict,
you can write this down if you like,
I predict in 20 years that parishes
that are-
using some language other than English are largely going to be small, isolated, and in major urban areas, and
everything else is going to be all English.
That's my prediction.
I mean, there could be changes, but that's what I think is going to happen.
And by the way, I should emphasize, in no way am I an English-only ideologue, I think if you have people in your parish,
whatever language they speak, you need to minister to them in that language.
And in many cases, it's going to be a mix, you know?
because not just because there are people here who they...
that's the case, but we have immigrants coming,
and an immigrant should not show up
and not be able to find a priest
that they can't hear their confession.
So we have ministry to do to immigrants as well,
and that's really an important thing,
and we shouldn't be afraid of that.
We should not be afraid of that.
It's okay, because remember the move,
even if you are like,
we need more English, more English, more English,
which is cool, that's the way it's going,
so you can take some time to minister to immigrants as well.
Like it's okay, it's all right.
Because the truth is,
immigrants their grandchildren.
will be English speakers.
That's just the way it's gonna be.
That's how immigration works.
Yeah.
Yeah, I don't buy that whole ugly American bit
at the end there.
But, uh, monolingualism.
You're five different ancient forms of English.
Don't count as other languages, Father Andrew.
I do read the gospel.
Is he a God of New Vespers gospel in Old English?
If anyone would like to have that at your paris.
Are you ever going to come and do it?
Absolutely.
So, my impression to the future is a little more cosmopolitan, shall we say, in America.
That may be because I live in a French-speaking region of the country.
So, you all should do more French in Louisiana.
We do.
And parts of Canada, they're sure you're more French.
I want to do more than that.
I want to do a little bit of an apology for the bad Greeks.
Wow.
Yeah, who gets stereotyped a lot.
They do.
So, and I'll say first,
I mean, there are some Greek parishes that are exploding with converse.
Exactly. I should have said that.
There are some Greek parishes exploding with converse.
My own wife who is pretty much my favorite person.
Does she feel the same about you?
Most days.
Came into the church through a Greek church, through St. Paul's and Irvine, California,
who welcomed her and loved her from the second she walked to the door, handed her a stack
of Catechese's books for free.
Right?
Just, I mean...
They're doing amazing things there and that's a Greek church. Okay, so this is not
But there's this there's other Greek folks who get pegged is there the the bad
They're the unwelcoming ones. They're just there because they're Greek
It's an ethnic club
Right and you get some of that rhetoric sometimes on some of the websites of you know, we're heard to sort of the spirit of
Hellenism and you know this kind of thing okay, so
I came out of I grew up in the
the Dutch reform church, which I know is weird now for Protestantism to have an ethnic
Protestant church, but it was one.
And so, right, first, Christian reform church was on church street.
In the town I grew up in, the Christian school was next door.
I went to school in church with the same kids.
They were all blonde-haired blue-eyed.
They all had names that started with Van and Van der or ended in strah.
Right like it was just all Dutch people
all the time. When I asked my dad, you know, what's a Lutheran? He said, that's where
German people go to church, right? What's a Roman Catholic? That's where Mexicans and
Irish people and Italians go to church, right? That was his, why do we go to our church?
Because we're Dutch. This was so ingrained in me that when I was going to go to
Protestant seminary, I had to get a recommendation from one of the church elders. And the
The church elder asked me.
Do you think when you're done with seminary you're going to try to get ordained in this church?
And I couldn't fathom the question.
I literally stared at him for like 10 seconds like, what?
Are there other churches?
Yes, I'm Dutch, right? Like this is it.
So, in the 1990s, two things happened simultaneously.
They decided they needed to grow.
grow. They started setting these ambitious growth plans.
One of them was called 2000 by 2000.
They wanted 2000 parishes by the year 2000.
They wanted to grow their population numbers.
We need to reach out.
We need to evangelize and grow all of our churches.
And they said, what's the biggest obstacle?
Well, we got all these old Dutch people.
And they're just here because they're Dutch.
All they care about is being Dutch.
want to sing Dutch hymns at Christmas.
They want to, you know, all of this stuff, all these Dutch traditions.
And so when people come, they don't feel welcomed, because they're not part of one of these Dutch families,
we need to downplay get rid of all this Dutch-Dutchness stuff.
We need to be more American, which meant being more evangelical.
Right?
Today, they have under 900 parishes.
They have the opposite problem we have with growth.
are closing.
churches everywhere.
Because what happened was all those Dutch people
were now unwelcome and they left.
And so these Greek people who sometimes we want to
stereotype and blame are honestly scared about this
happening to their church.
And it can happen to their church if they try to
Americanize in the wrong ways.
So this is a fear that they have and it's a fair fear.
And we need to, as Father Andrew was saying, we need to integrate new people with the old
people.
And this can happen in our parishes too.
This is just a Greek thing.
We need to integrate the new people and the old people, but part of that integration has
to be that we don't value the new people more than the old people.
I don't care if they're only there because they're Lebanese.
They're in the church.
receiving this accrimates.
Right? I don't care why you think they're there. I don't care if they cause problems with
the program you're proposing. Right? I don't care if they want to slam on the brakes all
the time for things. You need somebody there to slam on the brakes sometimes.
Yeah. Right? We have to value both equally. Right? We need not be off putting to the
new people because of them, nor off putting to them because of the new people. We need
to integrate them into one community.
I think I was first.
Hello.
I go by Mary Fox.
I'm at St. Nicholas,
I do church school.
I recall a couple of years back
we were doing the Romans curriculum.
The archdiocese rolled out.
I recall that in the Romans curriculum
we learned that there was...
that the historical background for the Book of Romans was that while there was a Jewish exile that took place,
that a lot of Gentiles started filling in the churches.
And this destabilized the community when the Jews returned to their churches and
found out that the Gentiles had now taken on a lot of the leadership roles and
whatever in the Roman church community.
So...
I was wondering if you guys can answer this question.
How can the Book of Romans provide us with some guidance for integrating newcomers into our church communities in a way that doesn't destabilize the community?
I mean, this is literally like several episodes of the whole Council of God podcast.
I was literally the consultant on that curriculum.
I know.
I was like, oh that's right, you helped right there, could be crazy.
I mean, you're the expert of when I come on, you'll like.
Yeah, so in fact, that was one of the things we talked about when we were putting the curriculum together,
because I talked about that, and I said, I think there are some things here that can help with those kind of issues in the parish.
We were a little careful and the curriculum writers.
So when I say I could sell, I could salt.
I go and I do a presentation.
and try to break down Romans and give ideas for here's the lessons, but they're really talented and skilled curriculum writers who go and then write the actual on the ground thing.
Because I can't necessarily prepare the lesson for five year olds and eight year olds and 12 year olds.
I have more of a little bit of the adult lessons maybe, but it says they're preparing that we didn't want to push that element into parishes where that wasn't an issue and make it an issue.
Right.
even though I think there are things addressed.
That's why we didn't go into that as far as we might have in the curriculum.
So yeah, so what happens for people who aren't familiar with that part of the curriculum,
is that the emperor Claudius at a certain point expelled all of the Jews from the city of Rome.
And it's mentioned in the book of Acts, that's why St. Paul meets St. Priscilla and Aquila.
So, in Corinth, as we-
because they had lived in Rome and they had been thrown out.
And it had gone to Corinth.
And so in the wake of that, the non-Jewish Christians,
the Gentile Christians, were still there.
And so the church was functioning with them doing everything.
They took over the leadership roles.
They were making everything happen.
And then after a couple of years, Claudius rescinded his edict
and the Jews, including the Jewish Christians,
because they did the right...
Germans didn't discriminate.
The Jewish came back.
And so now the Jewish Christians come back and whatever they used to do in the community
is now being done by some non-Jewish person.
And so a big part of what St. Paul is doing in his epistle to the Romans and why he goes
back and forth, he'll talk to Gentiles and then he'll talk to Jewish people and then
he'll talk to Gentiles and then he'll talk to Jewish Christians right back and forth
is that he's trying to help the
then reintegrate and come back together.
It's amazing how well now in our current day a lot of the things that he says to the
Jewish Christians apply to a lot of our cradle Orthodox people.
And Paul sort of expresses it as thankfulness.
You've had the scriptures, you've had the services of the church, you've grown up singing
learning the hymns, right?
You've had this incredible gift and that gift that you've had has shaped you, right?
In ways that the newcomers should be envious of, right?
At the same time, you haven't gotten everything perfect, right?
Where your centers do just like the newcomers, right?
But you have this rich heritage and this rich gift and the newcomers have this zeal.
They have talents and skills.
they have things they bring.
with them as they come to the church that they have to contribute to the church.
And so I think a big starting point in terms of a lesson we can learn to help us is having
both groups respect those gifts of the other.
So the newcomers respect the people who have been, maybe the person who's been Orthodox
their whole life and is now in their 50s or 60s, maybe they can't tell you the dates
of all the ecumenical cap.
right? That doesn't mean they don't know anything about the orthodox faith. Right? They know the orthodox faith. Right? It's in their bones. They really know it. Right? And teaching the newcomer to respect that. Right?
Right? Right away when you do that, you've already changed how that newcomer thinks about the faith.
You're helping teach them that it's not about the intellectual ideas and you
memorizing facts from books you read, and what preposites
We should use this theological statement, but it's about how you live your life and who you are.
Right? And what you do, they can learn that lesson.
And then helping the people who have been there and who have that gift,
helping them learn to appreciate the different gifts that the new people coming in bring.
Right? Which first of all may just be zeal.
and desire to tell other people about the Orthodox faith.
Right?
And...
and it's desire to learn more about the Orthodox faith.
And not to mention all the little contributions
of the things they've gotten good at.
They may show up less so now, unfortunately,
but older generations, you have some kid who grew up
Baptist going to Oana.
They're going to be able to quote the Bible.
They have a familiarity and a knowledge of the Bible
that very few people in any church do.
Okay.
And so there are going to be things they see in the liturgy
and recognize from different parts of skewer parts of the Bible
they've memorized that the priest may be clueless about.
I may have never noticed.
Because he's not as familiar with second chronicles.
As this guy is who's sort of about it.
There are all kinds of gifts that people bring in with them.
Ready to be employed.
And I think if we can help teach both groups to appreciate
gives to the other.
It'll be to the benefit of everybody.
Yeah.
Amen.
You're next.
So basically recently, I've visited a bunch of monasteries
and they all had icons of the last judgment.
And I saw people burning in hell and in hell.
And I was wondering if you could explain
a little bit of what it means.
Like, you know, like, um, since just like what it means.
like figure tifly. And like I just don't really like understand like why it's like I don't
know. I just like wonder if you could just like explain.
Yeah, yeah. So the question is, you know, what is going on with those people burning in
hell on last judgment icons? Why is that there? Yeah. Well, one thing I think everyone
should often take note of is that
Usually it's not just a big fire.
On the bottom where these people are burning,
there's a big mouth of like a dragon or a serpent
that's swallowing them, which is called a hell mouth,
which is one of my favorite words ever.
Right next to the word psychopomp,
which I was discussing with some people earlier today.
Um.
And so the hell mouth actually goes all the way back
all the way back to Genesis chapter.
Three where
God says to the serpent when he's cursing when he's pronouncing cursors over the serpent and over Adam and Eve
You know, he says the serpent you're gonna eat dust
Well, you know if you recall in Genesis. We've seen dust before
Adam is made from dust and God is just now telling them that they're about to go back to dust
dust.
Dust is what humans are made from and what we're going to go back.
And so the reason we go back to it is that's part, that's one image of what death is, right?
And so then what God is saying is that the serpent,
swallowing dust is an image of eating dead humans.
Right? And so you see in the last judgment icon of literally a gigantic serpent eating dead humans.
Okay? And, you know, I know some people say, well, you know,
Well, you know, that serpent may not...
not be the devil, blah, blah, blah.
But I mean, it says in Hebrews that the one who has the power of death is the devil.
That's exactly what St. Paul says.
The one who has the power of death, that is the devil.
Like he explicitly says that.
So all these things are connected together.
And so in a sense, what happens to the serpent there in Genesis 3 is he's essentially becoming
kind of the death god.
Like he's the one who controls the dead.
So what happens at the harrowing of Hades, which in some cases, there are some depictions
of the Herring of Hades where Christ is rescuing Adam and Eve.
and all the righteous prophets, that he's dragging them out of the mouth of this serpent,
bringing them out of the Hellmouth.
There's actually one version that talks of the harrowing of Hades from the church fathers
and I'm trying to remember if it was from Chrysostom or somebody else, which talks about Christ
entering into the mouth of the serpent and slashing it around from the inside.
he cuts the thing up from the inside which is kind of a-
But you know, I'm super into that, that, you know, sort of mythic language, you know.
You're an inter-13 year old boy.
That's right. Wait, Duff, do you doubt it inside?
So then the question ultimately is like, well, why is this image on the last judgment icon, right?
So this is, I mean, it can be a very scary image, depending on, especially how the iconographer paints it.
Well, think about where you're encountering that.
You're encountering that in a church.
I think you said you saw it in a monastery, right?
So you do see it in monastery churches, not all of them, but some.
And you see it in parish churches as well.
And often it's the back of the church.
So as you're leaving church, suddenly you're confronted,
like in many churches you'll see the Dormition of the Theotocos,
but in other ones you'll see the last judgment.
Christ in His glory, judging the whole world and down at the bottom,
this that you're talking about.
So that means that most people who are seeing that image are Christians.
So why would you put that image in front of them?
As Father Stephen is like to say in some of our Lord of
Spirit's podcasts, hell is for Christians.
And what is meant by that is the image of hell is presented in
the scriptures.
If you look in the scriptures, wherever hell is described,
wherever damnation is described, actually to be more precise.
Wherever damnation is described,
gurning forever, whatever, it's described to believers.
And so like, especially for those of you who grew up Baptist, where you were taught,
everybody is conceived on their way to be burning in hell unless they make a decision for
Christ and then you get out.
I was raised with that idea, probably some of you as well.
The Bible never says that.
Domination is never threatened against unbelievers.
It's described and presented to believers.
And the reason it's presented to believers is so that we would repent.
so that we would be
committed in our struggle to be like Christ.
And so when you see that as a possibility,
then that can help to motivate you.
Now, the great thing about the last judgment icon
is that that's not the only thing going on in it,
although it might be the most for us,
maybe the most interesting thing in the picture, I don't know.
Especially when you sometimes see, like,
there's demonic figures that are sort of like feeding people
to the dragon kind of thing, which is super fun and scary.
at the same time.
The whole icon, you see Christ in glory and then at his right hand is his mother and at his left hand is John the
forerunner and Baptist.
Right? And then surrounding are the ranks of the angels and then surrounding them and often below them are the many, many ranks of scenes.
Right? And so what you're being presented with is the life of the age to come all at once.
The good end the bad.
But what's beautiful about it is typically the
good is way bigger part of the icon than the bad.
And all of it's being presented to you, like,
okay, down here is the possibility of what could happen
if we decide not to repent.
If we turn her back on Christ and say,
I don't want you, I don't need you,
I'm gonna live life my way.
I'm gonna live life making me happy.
And forget everybody else, right?
If you dedicate yourself to that, then yes,
that could be your future.
But if you dedicate yourself to faithfulness
life in Christ.
then we can be standing alongside all of those saints.
We just celebrated the feast of all saints,
and the icon of all saints is basically the top part,
isn't it?
The top part of the last judgment icon,
the demination of stuff is not down there.
It's Christ and Throne and glory surrounded by His angels
and all of the saints.
And so that image is given to us in all of its parts
together, it's given to us so that we would repent.
On the one hand, I'm repenting.
because I don't want this part,
but I'm repenting because I want this part, right?
And so that's what's going on.
And remember, when you see something in church,
when you hear something in church,
when you experience something in church,
you always apply it to yourself.
Why is this here for me?
Not, oh look, I see bad people
and I can tell bad people that they're going to hell.
No, no, no, it's like this is a possibility for me.
So I need to recommit myself to repentance.
Does that make sense?
I cribbed half of that from you anyway.
I don't know what else you got to add.
I'll pick on that Baptist view briefly a little more.
Okay, it's good.
No, because this is something I have to tell people a lot who are coming into the church
from a Protestant background.
And it still amazes me that I have to say this.
God loves you and he wants you to find salvation.
He's not trying to weed you out.
He's not looking for an excuse.
He's not looking for some sin you forgot to confess
to use as an excuse to send you to hell.
Okay, both Christ and St. Matthew's Gospel
and St. John in the book of Revelation,
talk about the lake of fire that you see in the icon.
They say that was prepared for the devil and his angels.
That's why that exists, not for people.
And the scriptures tell us God wills
that no one should perish, but that all...
should come to the knowledge of the truth. That's what God wants. He's not trying to send you to
hell. What we need to do is cooperate with that. Accept and return his love, and we do that
through our actions. Christ says, right, if you love me, you will keep my commandments. Those go
together. So that's how we return His love. And if we're pursuing that and we're failing
We're peacefully pursuing that and we're repenting of our sins.
You don't have to sit around being scared that you miss something and God's going to send
you to hell because He doesn't want to.
God's looking for an excuse not to send you to hell.
Right?
There are lots of stories.
I won't take the time to tell them, but there are lots of stories in the Orthodox World
Menastic stories about God saving someone through one decent thing they did, right?
in their life.
even though this was a miserable person otherwise, right?
They did one good thing, and God saves them through that.
That's who our God is.
Right?
And so, when you look at that image, when you look at the image of Christ being crucified,
you should not be terrified of God and how much He hates sin including yours.
You should see images of love.
of the love of the God who has saved us.
from all that. Amen. Amen. We're going to go for about 15 more minutes so that we don't run
up against the Vespers but yeah yeah. Come on come on come on down. You're like the next contestant.
That dates us as well. Get my Rod Rodion. So I come from Parish that has dozens of catacumans,
myself being one of them in that group there are
a lot of YouTube videos, Instagram Reels always being passed around.
Oh boy.
So my question is, what's your advice for discerning online information,
orthodoxy, pseudo orthodoxy, as well as just navigating just the barrage of everything
the internet throws at you on a daily basis?
That's a great question. I'll have a quick answer here for you because I just,
But I want to make sure I get this right.
Okay, hold on.
There's about 12 hours a week of me.
I know.
So it used to be, it was just me.
Just watch that and you don't need to spend more than 12 hours a week on the internet.
That's right.
Sorry.
Okay, so yeah, I mean, I basically work on the internet.
This is essentially what I do.
And I'm super aware of all of the dangers of that.
And I get, I get asked essentially this question a lot.
And I've thought about the best way to answer this.
And I concluded that St. Paul gave the answer in Galatians chapter 5.
So here's what he says, and this is starting with verse 16.
But I say walk by the Spirit and you will not gratify the desires of the flesh.
For the desires of the flesh are against the Spirit and the desires of the Spirit are against the flesh
for these are opposed to each other to keep you from doing the things you want to do.
But if you're a led by-
the spirit you are not under the law. Now the works of the flesh are evident, sexual
immorality, impurity, sensuality, idolatry, sorcery, enmity, strife, jealousy, fits of
anger, rivalries, defensions, divisions, envy, drunkenness, orgies, and things like these.
I warned you as I warned you before.
that those who do such things will not inherit the kingdom of God.
But the fruit of the Spirit is love, joy, peace, patience, kindness, goodness, faithfulness, gentleness, self-control.
Against such things there is no law.
And those who belong to Christ Jesus have crucified the flesh with its passions and desires.
If we live by the Spirit, let us also keep in step with the Spirit.
Let us not become conceded, provoking one another, and being one another.
Now, there are a lot of arguments and all kinds of stuff that goes on on orthodoxy in
the internet, but I think if we sat down in Regulations Chapter 5, it actually, it all
becomes so super clear what you should pay attention to and what you should not.
Makes sense.
I'm not saying that those who are participating in kind of the dark side of orthodoxy
Internet have nothing good to say.
that I probably don't agree with 90% of the things
that they say, I probably agree with most of it.
But the spirit with which that side delivers those things
is also being communicated.
And so the truth is, is you don't need any of it.
I work on the internet, I produce stuff on the internet.
You don't need anything that I make.
My stuff you do.
You don't need it.
anything that bothers you. See that now we're having a
descent and strife. Yes. What you've caused. I know, I know. You don't need any of it.
You don't. If it helps you, do the 3D thing in your parish. Thank God. If it helps
your priest, take care of you. Thank God. If when you watch it or listen to it or read it,
you want to repent of your
sins. Thank God. If it's leading you somewhere else, go read a book. Do something. Take a walk.
Take care of somebody. Make something for someone. Pray for somebody. You know, when the judgment
comes, I mean you've read Matthew chapter 25, I'm sure. It doesn't say, you know, and then you know,
he sit on his glorious throne and judge people by their correct opinions that they posted on Twitter.
We will be judged on what we have done.
And so if the content you consume assists you in that good, you still don't need it.
You don't need it.
So yeah, I mean, doom scrolling is a pastoral issue of our talk.
And there's all kinds of, I mean, there's worse things that you could be watching than
even this kind of stuff we've just been talking about.
There's way worse things.
You know, um, but.
But yeah, I think, like I said, I feel like it's really straightforward and clear.
Once you actually, like, let's get back to what the Scriptures say and what Christ says and
what is a Apostle say.
And then, you don't need a list.
I've had people say, can you give me a list?
I'm like, nope, no lists.
But I'm going to give you those verses to read.
And I think you don't need a theological degree to understand what those verses say.
You don't.
all is just so crystal clear at them.
moment. So yeah. Thank you. So now we crib that from St. Paul. I know. So like Pablo Capicaso
said good artist plagiarized great artist steel. That's right. So that's.
Big God. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. I have a couple questions. I may have misheard but I thought I
heard that there was going to be a like a standardized catachesus curriculum kind of in the
I was just wondering if that was them.
I have also heard that.
Okay.
I hear things.
Yeah.
I don't know.
See it there.
Are you allowed to say anything about that or?
I think a sample has been sent to select priests.
Yeah.
A sample has been sent to select priests.
I also had another question.
I was not selected.
Why?
You're not one of the elect.
Why the Archdiocese?
By the Archdiocese.
Yeah.
Okay.
You were talking about the apotoxis.
Apotoxys. Yes. And there's a line where it says, now breathe and spit. Is that like a
breath where you're inhaling or are you exhaling the devil and his demons out of you?
How many people have wondered what that whole breathe thing is? And you see a breathe
and spit upon them. That's what the priest says, which is a little weird, right? So one
thing I want to say that's going to be very disappointing for people is the spitting
as a relatively late.
development. It's everybody's favorite part. It's an accretion and accretion. Well, that's
a deep karabura. But the breathing okay. So there's not that's not the only breathing
that happens. Of course, the priest, priest, breathes on the person who's being received
at that moment as well. The whole breathing thing is about exorcism and also about giving
the
Holy Spirit, right?
So you notice, for instance, when Christ gives the Holy Spirit to his disciples after the
resurrection, it says, and he breathed on them and said, receive the Holy Spirit.
So that's what's going on there, the exhalation that is going, it's really hard to translate,
it's more like blow him out.
You know, like breathe out the demons.
Cool.
As it were.
And then the priest breathes on them.
So yeah, there's a lot of blowing that goes on and it has to do with exorcism and also
giving of the Holy Spirit at the same time.
It's a much kind of under-discussed detail in the baptism, but I think super interesting
actually.
Very worth it.
Yeah, yeah.
And there's breathing that goes on like when the water is blessed for the baptism again,
the priest.
Hmm.
Right in the form of a cross like all that's going on
You know
People blinking when you breathe the priest breathe in their face. I've seen a lot of blinks. You know
Babies will hold their breath. I always eat a big raw onion
They could feel the exercise happening
Yeah, no that that goes but the the breathing as part of exorcism rituals goes back even pre-Christian
into like second-tumble judies.
and even into the Old Testament.
Because breath, spirit, these are the same word,
the same kind of concept and wind.
Yeah.
Thank you Father.
Yeah, great question.
That's a very LOS kind of question right there.
That's good.
All right, we still have about 10 minutes.
Come on, come on, come on.
Come on.
Hello, my name is Jordan.
Earlier you were saying like if you're in your parish,
take care of it,
And you said that's like the
responsibility of the parish. How do you tread the line though if imbalance if
You're new to the faith so you don't want to teach someone
Necessarily because you're not properly categorized or
Like know everything. How do you balance that line from like taking care of your parish?
But not overstep in boundaries to where you're you're
Now getting into the role of somewhere like clergy
Yeah
How do you not do too much to...
or whatever. Well one thing we have to realize is that the clergy's role is not like the top.
Like it's we're not all aspiring to be clergy. Please don't. Not for everybody, but for the people
that God chooses and that the bishop recognizes and so forth. But I think that there's some things
that can be done that by no means are kind of putting yourself above other people and it's the practical
things within the church, right?
Like no church should have to hire a cleaning service.
Many of our parishes do.
Maybe once in a while you need to hire somebody
who can like buff the floor or something like that
because you don't have that skill or that equipment.
Okay, I understand that.
But like, or like landscaping,
you know, cleaning the bathrooms.
Or I mean, there's a million other practical things
to do in church life,
and it's still usually the 20% who are doing all of it.
Right.
Those are things that no matter how new you are,
you can jump into.
And the key is you find someone you see someone doing
one of those things, say, hey, can I give you a hand?
What needs to be done?
That hasn't been done.
You know?
And I mean, if all else fails, you ask the priest,
say, hey, I'm here to help.
Send me to somebody.
Which, hey, I'm here to help, is like the most musical thing
that a priest can hear.
You know, he may not have even know where to send you,
but he'll be just so overjoyed that you said that sentence to him.
It's true, right?
Right, fathers?
Yeah, absolutely.
I'm here to help.
What?
So, yeah, there's all kinds of things that can be done without, like there's certain kinds
of jobs that you do need to be cataclyzed, like being a teacher, for instance, or being,
you know, someone who's administering the parish in some way, like to serve in the parish
council, there needs to be some more formation there.
But there's all kinds of things that can't or you don't like like joining the choir
you should at least be able to sing.
Someone else should say that you are able to sing.
Dang it.
I wanted to be in the choir.
Not everybody has every gift father.
It's OK.
But yeah, there's all kinds of things that can be done.
So without, like I said, without, so just ask.
You see someone doing something, especially if you think
yourself I could do that.
That isn't a matter of telling other people.
ask, how can I help?
And sometimes the people who have been doing a job a long time, it may be difficult for
them to actually have help offer to them.
So their first response might be, oh, I got this.
And it might also be like, I've been in some parishes where people have been doing one
thing for so long that that's their identity at church.
And so, and someone else says, hey, I want to help, they're kind of like, don't take away
my thing.
You know
But the truth is, there's so many people showing up in our doors now.
There is plenty of work for everyone.
There's plenty of work for everybody.
So yeah, just find some practical thing.
And if you find yourself in the parish bathroom, right, and there's toilet paper on the floor,
I have watched the same piece of toilet paper sit on the floor of a bathroom in a church for weeks.
Here's the airing of grievances.
Yeah, exactly.
you know, and then I realized why did you not?
I picked that up, Father Andrew.
Where people need to have that same thoughts.
Like there's obvious, and my wife often says this to me,
why did you walk past that?
So which is a good question.
So yeah, yeah, there's all kinds of things
that obviously need to be done that no one's
going to object to.
Sounds like you're saying focus on the little things,
because they're very important.
Especially the practical things.
Let me add to that.
There's a tendency.
that we need to stop, which is to think of the church building as the community.
Indeed.
The community is the community of people.
And the church building is the building that the community owns where they gather to worship.
Right?
But you can serve the community outside of the church building, right, outside of church
hours.
There are people, there are elderly people in your parish, I guarantee you, who need their
not just
church is long.
Who needs some help around the house?
Who needs some help doing everyday things?
And if you can't find someone like that,
one of the many things I learned from my father,
my father in his later years, was distressed by the fact
that every time one of the elders in our community passes away,
the stories of their life, the things they learned,
All those-
experiences, they don't vanish completely,
but they vanish from our world and our lives.
And so my dad started just visiting people
in the community.
He would just go and sit for an hour or two
with an elderly person who's sitting at home
all day by themselves.
And your dad was not clergy, right?
My dad was not clergy.
Right.
You didn't even have to say anything, you would just listen.
And because of that, I know all these stories
about the Dutch resistance in World War II.
Right, but these stories that otherwise would have vanished and some of them are funny and some of them are heartbreaking and some of them are
Wonderful and some of them there's all kind and you can learn from every one of them, right and
That's something anyone can do
If you can hear
Right you can go and sit for an hour with someone and just listen to them and learn from them and
Pick up that wisdom and pass it on and make sure it doesn't vanish
So there are things like anybody.
can do. I'm aware of parishes where there are groups, particularly of men, but I mean
you could just, you know, you taught us Mutantus suggests if it's a group of women or a mixed
group or whatever, particularly a group of men and what they do is they ask the priest
or whoever who in the parish needs some help and then a group of them show up to the house,
which is usually much like if it's just one person that could be, it could potentially
be a little weird or threatening, you know, if it's not a relation that there already
exists. But if a group like this is the
ministry and we're here today to landscape your house. We're here today to clean the whole thing.
We're here today to fix all the stuff around your house that you haven't gotten to.
You know, whatever it might be. And that is such a powerful expression of love. And when you're
doing it with other group of people, then what it does is, number one, it says to the person who's
receiving that, this community loves you and cares for you. But also the people who are doing that together.
some of them might...
brand new to the church. Hey man, we're going to do their lawn. Come with us. It's integrating them
into serving together with other people and creating friendships and relationships as well. So it
has multiple beautiful benefits. Yeah, actually. Yeah, thanks for bringing that. That's a really good
point. Yeah, yeah. Thank you. Thank you guys. Well, God bless. All right. Well, it's quarter till.
So, you have anything you want to correct or add the order?
Nothing to correct
Thank you fathers
I promised them at the beginning that if they make a mistake I will correct them loudly and rudely
That was a joke of course
But that was wonderful and thank you very much for being here and taking the time to
Have this panel discussion and tomorrow today we've had the broccoli said yeah
is the broccoli, tomorrow is the meat.
Tomorrow is the meat.
So come back tomorrow and listen again, God willing.
We have 15 minutes to get used to,
to get ready for respos.
And it is next door to your,
to your route.
God bless you.
We'll see you at respos.
Thank you, Shana.
Thank you, everybody.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father
Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient
faith radio.
And I be held, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne, and the beasts,
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000, and thousands of thousands,
with a loud voice, worthy is the land that...
a slain to receive power and riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.